Hornbooks, ca. 1550-1986 LT109 .A1
Lilly Library
Hornbooks
ca. 1550-1986
Lilly Library
LT109 .A1
31 Items
The collection consists of a group of 28 hornbooks. Also included are two auction catalogs for sales where some of the hornbooks were sold and a description of a hornbook in brass from dealer Patrick King's list no. 11, 1986.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Historical Note
Hornbooks were once common objects used to teach children the alphabet and reading-readiness skills.
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists of a group of 28 hornbooks, most of which are from the library of Elisabeth Ball. Also included are two auction catalogs for sales where some of the hornbooks were sold and a description of a hornbook in brass from dealer Patrick King's list no. 11, 1986.
Related Material
Seven of the hornbooks are described and illustrated in Tuer's History of the hornbook (London: Leadenhall Press, 1897), also located at the Lilly Library, Indiana University, Bloomington, Indiana. References to this work in the descriptions are cited as Tuer and page number.
Acquisition Information
Acquired: August 1983
Provenance
Items 1-27 and 29-30 from the library of Elisabeth Ball. These had belonged to the collector C.T. Owen and some had also belonged to A.W. Tuer.
Hornbooks --Specimens.; Hornbooks --Bibliography --Catalogs.
- Hornbooks, ca.1550-1986
  - Ivory. 7 cm. x 13.3 cm., Capital alphabet, small alphabet with long "s," vowels, numerals, and floral design engraved on front.; Arms of a previous owner engraved at base. Engraved line border. Hole in handle for suspension. In brown leather case. (Item 1)
    Related Materials
    No. 1 in Grafton and Hurcombs auction catalogs (see items 29 and 30).
  - Ivory. 5.4 cm. x 10.9 cm., Engraved on front with capital alphabet, on back with small alphabet with long "s," and vowels.; Each side framed by engraved line. Floral decoration on both sides of handle. In brown leather case. (Item 2)
    No. 2 in Grafton and Hurcombs auction catalogs (see items 29 and 30).
  - Ivory. 5.9 cm. x 12.4 cm., Capital alphabet, small alphabet with long "s," and vowels engraved in black on front. Separated by floral decorations.; An engraved bird (the crest of the Tallow Chandlers Company, one of the City guilds) on handle. Hole in handle for suspension. Numerous scratches. In brown leather case. (Item 3)
    No. 3 in Grafton and Hurcombs auction catalogs (see items 29 and 30).
  - Ivory. 4.7 cm. x 10.4 cm., 1774; Capital alphabet engraved on front; small alphabet engraved on back.; Engraved line border around both sides, except for handle which has floral decorations. "A. M. 1774" carved on one edge. Numerous scratches. In brown leather case. (Item 4)
    No. 5 in Grafton and Hurcombs auction catalogs (see items 29 and 30).
    Companion hornbook to no. 5.
  - Ivory. 4.8 cm. x 10.5 cm., 1774; Capital alphabet engraved on front; small alphabet engraved on back.; Simple floral decoration on both sides of handle. "W. M. 1774" carved on one edge. Numerous scratches. In brown leather case. (Item 5)
    No. 8 in Grafton and Hurcombs auction catalogs (see items 29 and 30).
    Companion hornbook to no. 4.
  - Ivory. 5.3 cm. x 11 cm., Capital alphabet engraved on front; small alphabet with long "s," and vowels on back.; Line border on both sides. Floral decoration on both sides of handle. Cracks show where hornbook was broken, although it has been repaired. In brown leather case. (Item 6)
    No. 9 in Grafton and Hurcombs auction catalogs (see items 29 and 30).
  - Ivory. 5.4 cm. x 10.9 cm., Capital alphabet engraved on front with letters colored by black pigment. Small alphabet with long "s," and vowels on back, also engraved and colored.; Floral decoration on both sides of handle. Engraved line border. In brown leather case. (Item 7)
    No. 12 in Grafton and Hurcombs auction catalogs (see items 29 and 30).
  - Ivory. 3.5 cm. x 10 cm., Capital alphabet engraved on front; small alphabet with long "s," and numerals engraved on back.; Hole in handle for suspension. In brown leather case. (Item 8)
    No. 13 in Grafton and Hurcombs auction catalogs (see items 29 and 30).
  - Ivory. 16 cm. x 20.6 cm., late 18th century; Black capital alphabet engraved on front. Engraved on back: "And/Lord. Lady. Mr. Mrs./Miss. Today. Tomorrow./Yesterday. Read./Very well. Bateman./Fire. Dogs. Chaise. Walk./Ride. Glass. Rain. Dry." This hornbook said to have been used to teach the children of the Duke of Marlborough. "Bateman" said to have been the name of the family's favorite nurse.; Handle cracked. In brown leather case. (Item 9)
    See Tuer, p. 454-456, for illustration and description.
    No. 40 in Grafton and Hurcombs auction catalogs (see items 29 and 30).
  - Bone. 3.8 cm. x 10.8 cm., Capital alphabet engraved on front. Small floral design underneath alphabet. Engraved floral decoration covers the back.; Hole in handle for suspension. In brown leather case. (Item 10)
    No. 6 in Grafton and Hurcombs auction catalogs (see items 29 and 30).
  - Boxwood. 4.3 cm. x 13.4 cm., 1744; Capital alphabet, small alphabet with long "s," vowels, Lord's Prayer, and decoration of fourteen fleurs-de-lis appear on front. Letters and fleurs-de-lis burnt into wood with binder's brass type. "Joseph Howell 1744" burnt into handle. Name repeated on back. Four lines border hornbook.; Top edge carved for decoration. Hole in handle for suspension. (Item 11)
    See Tuer, p. 168-169 for illustration and description.
    No. 36 in Grafton and Hurcombs auction catalogs (see items 29 and 30).
  - Wood, paper, horn, latten, nails. 5.4 cm. x 11 cm., Lesson sheet consists of printed small alphabet preceded by a cross and capital A; followed by vowels, capital alphabet, syllabarium, invocation, and Lord's Prayer. Text uses long "s."; Horn held by four latten strips and eight nails. Half of one latten strip missing. Ornamental border covered by latten strips. In brown leather case. (Item 12)
    No. 4 in Grafton and Hurcombs auction catalogs (see items 29 and 30).
  - Wood, paper, horn, latten, nails. 5.8 cm. x 10.8 cm., Lesson sheet consists of printed small alphabet preceded by a cross and a capital A; followed by vowels, capital alphabet, syllabarium, invocation, and Lord's Prayer. Text uses long "s."; Printed decoration borders sheet. Horn held by four latten strips and eight nails. Nail ends visible through back of wood. In brown leather case. (Item 13)
    No. 17 in Grafton and Hurcombs auction catalogs (see items 29 and 30).
  - Oak, paper, horn, brass, nails. 11.2 cm. X 18.7 cm., Lesson sheet consists of small alphabet preceded by a Cross and capital A; followed by vowels, capital alphabet, syllabarium, invocation, and Lord's Prayer. Text in manuscript uses long "s."; Four wide strips of brass fastened by ten iron nails. A crown and "W.F." carved on back. Handle has a hole for suspension. (Item 14)
    No. 14 in Grafton and Hurcombs auction catalogs (see items 29 and 30).
  - Cardboard and paper. 5.8 cm. X 9.5 cm., Early 19th century; Printed lesson sheet consists of small alphabet with Long "s," and capital alphabet, surrounded by ornamental border.; Varnish over lesson sheet has worn away in patches. Card covered by Dutch floral paper. (Handle defaced by piece of paper glued to it which gives a reference to Tuer and is marked by a "22" in blue pencil.) (Item 15)
    See Tuer, p. 350, for illustration and description.
    No. 21 in Grafton and Hurcombs auction catalogs (see items 29 and 30).
    Custodial History
    Andrew W. Tuer, who owned this hornbook, dates it from the opening years of the nineteenth century.
  - Silver, ivory, nails. 6.3 cm. x 10 cm., Silver plate, set in ivory frame, engraved with capital and small alphabets separated by a wavy line. Four silversmith's marks at top of silver plate. Front and back of ivory frame held by fourteen rivets. Engraved griffin decorates bottom of the frame and handle. Two engraved lines border the ivory frame. Hole in handle for suspension. Crack at top of ivory frame. In brown leather case. (Item 16)
    No. 10 in Grafton and Hurcombs auction catalogs (see items 29 and 30).
  - Silver, wood, paper, horn. 5.9 cm. x 11.1 cm., ca. 1550; Lesson sheet, printed in Black letter, consists of small alphabet preceded by a cross and a capital A; followed by vowels, capital letters, syllabarium, invocation, and Lord's Prayer. Text uses long "s." Silver frame with scalloped edge holds lesson sheet and horn, supported by thin piece of wood. Back of frame elaborately engraved with bird perched on a branch surrounded by foliage. The handle, which has been soldered to the frame, has an inverted tulip and and line border engraved on each side. (Item 17)
    This hornbook resembles one illustrated and described in Tuer, p. 102-103.
    Date from Grafton and Hurcombs auction catalogs (see items 29 and 30) where it is no. 23.
  - Brass. 6.5 cm. x 14.4 cm., 1729; Raised capital alphabet on front. On back is carved "St. Paul's Infant School A.D. 1729." Handle at top with hole for suspension. (Item 18)
    No. 37 in Grafton and Hurcombs auction catalogs (see items 29 and 30).
    See also No. 40 in Patrick King's list no. 11, 1986 (item 31 of this list).
  - Brass. 6.4 cm. x 14.1 cm., Raised capital alphabet on front. On back is carved "St. Mary's School Shrewsbury." Handle at top with hole for suspension. In brown leather case. (Item 19)
    No. 38 in Grafton and Hurcombs auction catalogs (see items 29 and 30).
  - Wood and paper. 5.6 cm. x 10.3 cm., 1810-1820; Printed lesson sheet consists of small alphabet preceded by an X and a capital A; followed by capital alphabet, syllabarium, and Lord's Prayer. Ornamental border. Underneath lower border is printed "Printed and sold by Howard and Evans, /42, Long-lane, Smithfield, London." Front is varnished. Lesson sheet attached to wood, which has been covered with Dutch floral paper. (Item 20)
    See Tuer, p. 350-351, for illustration and description.
    No. 42 in Grafton and Hurcombs auction catalogs (see items 29 and 30).
    Formerly part of Dr. Kenneth R.H. MacKenzie's hornbook collection.
  - Paper and horn. 8 cm. x 13.5 cm., 1784; Original hornbook consisted of a piece of printed paper, which was later mounted on a thick slab of horn. Printed lesson sheet, entitled "THE CHILD'S GUIDE TO HIS LETTERS," consists of small alphabet, capital alphabet, italic small alphabet, vowels, syllabarium, invocation, and Lord's Prayer. Text uses long "s." A cross appears underneath printers' names on handle and miniature crosses appear in breaks of the border. Decorative border. Imprint reads: "Glasgow:/Printed and sold by/J. & M. Robert- son,/ MDCCLXXXIV." (Item 21)
    See Tuer, p. 126, 129, 269, for illustration and description.
    No. 43 in Grafton and Hurcombs auction catalogs (see items 29 and 30).
  - Wood, horn, leather, nails, paint. 8.2 cm. x 30 cm., Carved and painted figure of a woman on back. Colors have faded but appear to have been red and black. On front, empty horn envelope is held by leather strip and nineteen nails. (Item 22)
  - Wood, horn, nails, gilt. 11.2 cm. x 26 cm., Raised carved figure of a kneeling angel on back. On front, empty horn envelope held by three rounded strips of wood. Strips painted gilt, though very worn. One nail visible. (Item 23)
  - Wood, horn, leather, tacks, metal. 8.7 cm. x 18.3 cm., On front, empty horn envelope held by leather strip and ten rounded tacks. On back is a simple abacus composed of three rusted thin metal rods, the ends bent and stuck into the wood, and nine wooden balls, four on the top rod, three on middle, two on bottom. Flecks of red and white paint on balls. Piece of brown string tied around handle. (Item 24)
  - Wood, horn, nails. 8.5 cm. x 17.3 cm., On front, empty horn envelope held by nineteen nails. Horn cracked and chipped. (Item 25)
  - Leather, horn, thread. 12 cm. x 20 cm., Two pieces of black leather stitched together and open at the top. Center cut out of front piece, forming a frame. Horn stuck between leather pieces. No lesson sheet. On back, figure of a rearing horse stamped in the center. (Item 26)
  - Wood, horn, leather, tacks, metal, paint. 14 cm. x 24 cm., On front, empty horn envelope held by leather strip and fifteen tacks. Horn cracked at the top. On the back, capital alphabet and numerals painted in red. Red painted line separates each row. Attached vertically to each side is a thin metal rod, ends bent and stuck into top and bottom edges of wood. Five carved beads threaded on each rod. Hole in handle for suspension. (Item 27)
  - Ivory. 4.8 cm. x 10 cm., late 18th/early 19th century; Capital alphabet engraved on front; small alphabet with long "s" on back. Letters colored with black pigment. Floral design on both sides of handle. (Item 28)
    See Tuer, p. 121, for illustration and description of a nearly identical item.
    From Lathrop C. Harper, 22 East 40th Street, New York, New York 10016. Received 1974.
  - Auction Catalog. "A remarkably fine collection of horn books which is considered to be absolutely unique, comprising as it does fifty genuine specimens in ivory, wood, silver, and brass The whole offered for sale by Grafton & Co., London.", 1923 (Item 29)
  - Auction Catalog. "Brief description of an unique collection of horn-books and juvenile literature, harlequinades, miniature bookcases, to be sold by auction at Hurcombs, Grafton Galleries, London.", 1931 (Item 30)
  - Patrick King. List no. 11.. Photocopy of pg. 14-15., 1986 (Item 31)